Fiji is a paradise in the South Pacific.
Unfortunately, the country has been
infiltrated by a doomsday cult,
Grace Road.
They ruled their members with an iron
fist while entangling international
authorities in a year'slong game of cat
and mouse. Unhindered, the cult built a
vast business empire stretching across
the island, warmly embraced by the local
government. [music]
Their ambitions seemed to be far from
over.
[music]
>> They expanded from 30 something
businesses to 54 in [music] the period
following the raids.
>> Do we look like a bird? There have been
allegations of being fed improperly,
being housed improperly, being
overworked, [music] well beyond what
normal labor practices would allow, and
physical punishments to top everything
off.
>> I realized my passport was gone. I was
panicking a lot. I was screaming for
help. This story is about religious
fanaticism. Actually, their whole
purpose is about preparing for great
tribulation or the Armageddon, the end
of days,
>> about a regime deeply entwined with
them. The church were able to ingratiate
themselves with senior people in the
government of the day, about freedom of
press.
>> Our latest investigation story or peace
is with our lawyers
>> that the permits given to your
production [music] company must be
cancelled forth with.
>> We're basically holding back the stories
>> in about an entire country [music] in
the chokeold of a sect. What happens if
you effectively kill this golden goose?
How did Grace Road amass so much power?
How far does its influence reach? And
why has no one stepped in to stop them?
Well, we went there ourselves [music]
to find out.
>> All right, it's the first day.
>> This investigation is of course a job
for Valley. He previously traveled to
Ethiopia for us where a new ocean is
forming. It doesn't take long to
convince him to go.
>> I was super happy when Fern asked me to
go to the other side of the world to
join a cult. I guess
>> now he's on a 48-hour trip from Vienna
to Fiji.
>> This is the farthest away I've ever been
from home. Literally the exact opposite
side of the world.
>> Voli will spend nearly a week in Fiji
speaking with all kinds of people about
Grace Road or at least trying to
>> grace.
Nothing much about them. I've heard lots
of rumors, but it was like out of my
business.
>> All I know is that they say they are a
Christian based uh restaurant, but from
what I've heard from rumors, they said
they're working under cults or something
like that.
>> I have had conversations with them. It's
a confidential meeting. So, I can't
[music] say more. From what I have
heard, it is enough for me to know that
this is not a church.
>> There are negative questions that only
Grace Road can answer. And uh to get an
answer of them right now, as you now
know, not very easy. They haven't talked
to us. They don't even know what we're
doing. And yet, they're trying to shut
us down. If that's not a red flag, I
don't know what is.
But let's go back to the beginning
before Valley's plane touched the ground
at 90. It all starts here in Soul, South
Korea, between auto repair shops in an
old factory building on a Sunday morning
in 2008. The woman in the blazer up
front is called Sheen Oko. She spent 3
years evangelicizing China, preached in
Philadelphia and in South Korea. She
claimed she was trained by the
Presbyterian Church. Back then, one of
the largest Christian denominations in
South Korea. But the Presbyterian Church
insists Shin's story is false. Not that
it matters much. By now, Shinn has her
own church, Grace Road. And she has some
pretty specific ideas about humanity's
future. Jesus, she says, will soon
return to Earth a second time. But
first, the world must endure a doomsday.
In South Korea, cults have been
flourishing for decades. In the early
2000s, an estimated 300,000 South
Koreans were said to belong to a 100
different groups. Today, more than 300
cults are active in the country. Some
experts trace this back to the national
trauma of colonialism and war. Back
then, cults offered social contacts,
comfort, and salvation. Today, they
promise secret knowledge, a path to
material and spiritual prosperity. Many
of these cults are controversial. Some
are outright dangerous. Over time, Shin
wins over hundreds of followers with her
rhetoric. In her mind, there is only one
way to escape the coming doom. They must
find the promised land where she and her
followers can survive global famine and
nuclear fallout.
Their plan was to establish these large
farms and to assist in helping feed the
world during a time of hardship. That
was the message that Okusin was
promulgating from her pulpit. Dan McGary
is an editor for the Pacific region with
the OCCRP, the Organized Crime and
Corruption Reporting Project. He's been
investigating Grace Road for years.
Around 2014, Shin's son, Daniel Kim,
takes up the quest to find said promised
land. He searches for a place with no
winter and a steady warmth between 20
and 30° C. In his pursuit, he allegedly
travels to 60 countries. And eventually
his search leads him to Fiji.
An archipelago 332 islands and over 500
islands. Scattered across an ocean
expands almost twice the size of the
Gulf of Mexico. Only a 100 are
inhabited. Fewer than 1 million people
live here. Most of them on the main
island Vidilv. That's also where the
capital Suva is located. Until 1970,
Fiji was part of the British Empire. So
English became the official language.
And because India was also under British
rule, many Indians ended up in Fiji.
Today, next to English, people here also
speak Fijian Hindi and traditional
Fijian i2K.
>> Like he said, at the end of the day,
only thing you hear is stories, but it's
uh important for us to see it and
believe it. We can't be depending on the
stories we hear.
>> Back in 2014, Kim wrapped up his
assessment of whether Fiji could be the
promised land. Now he's about to leave
for his next destination, Nepal. But he
gets stuck in Fiji and takes it as a
sign from God. His quest he believes
reached its conclusion. Soon after,
Grace Road announces they have clear
evidence. This is the land God has
prepared. And so, Prophet Kim's mother
and hundreds of church members follow
him there. Others believe no prolonged
search mission or higher power was
involved.
>> There used to be a direct flight from
Soul to Nandi. That's it. You know, it
was a direct flight. Reverend Bwan James
is the general secretary of the Pacific
Conference of Churches, an organization
to bring together different churches in
the Pacific region. He is also a
minister of Fiji's Methodist Church. I
can tell you that I have been aware of
the Grace Road uh group for about 11
years now. I was first approached by
Korean groups in Fiji, faith groups in
Fiji that are doing missionary work to
raise [music] their concerns about some
of the new sects that were coming in. It
wasn't just Fijians who were wary of
Grace Road. Back home in South Korea,
the Presbyterian Church launched an
investigation into Shinukjo and gathered
evidence of just how dangerous she was.
To heal a schizophrenic man, she ordered
her followers to tie him with duct tape.
The man's blood circulation failed and
his leg later had to be amputated. In
September 2014, the Presbyterian Church
declared Shin a heretic. Deacon Leing Yu
was one [music] of the ones leading the
charge against her. A grave insult, one
that would not go unanswered.
A Sunday morning, 3 months later, mass
is about to begin at the Dayroom
Methodist Church in Seoul. In front of
the church, a few dozen Christro members
are protesting. Suddenly, some of them
storm inside.
They violently attacked a church
official, Decon Lee and Guu. They grab
him and drag him down the stairs. They
probably consider him to be a demon. At
least that's what Chin reportedly told
them. She was never persecuted for the
attack. But afterwards, she was on the
radar of both the South Korean media and
police. All the more reason to finally
settle in Fiji for good.
This is the place that is supposed to
save a group of people from tamine and
nuclear fallout. A group of people that
came from 8,000 km away from here from
South Korea. I wonder also, you know,
all the people here in this bus and the
people around, how aware are they of
this sect and the stories around them?
How troubled is this paradise? is
paradise on earth really. It's like a
three four hour drive from Mali to Suba
and all along this road are actually
also graceful businesses,
supermarkets, gas stations, restaurants
and so on.
One should ask the question is why did
they come in as a business first rather
than as a church, right? So they had
obviously already a methodology, an
approach to come in. So they'll come in
as a business. They set up as an in
foreign investor and then they they move
from from there.
>> In April 2014, Grace Road established
their presence in Fiji with this farm.
3.8 hectares of land. More than enough
space to grow rice [music] and
vegetables.
So far so good. Given the whole incoming
global famine thing, it probably makes
sense to cultivate their own rice, feed
the world during a time of hardship, and
so on. But then something strange
started to happen. The cult started to
expand rapidly.
In 2015, they opened their restaurant,
Grace Road Kitchen, followed by Noodle
Story, Sunny Pizza, Awesome Grill,
Fierce Chicken, Snowy House, and
Petisserie Pacifica. Grace Road also
launched their own construction company,
designing and building for their own
businesses, for private clients, and
even for the government. As beits true
Christians, after Cyclone Winston in
2016, they helped rebuild this village.
A year later, they were busy
refurbishing and extending Prime
Minister Bayamara's house at a cost to
Fijian taxpayers of allegedly around $3
million. In the same year, the group won
a business award presented by Bayamara.
By this point, more than 100 Fijian
locals are working for Grace Road, but
the majority of employees are Korean, at
least 300, and they're far from done.
Grace Road opens supermarkets, hardware
[music] stores, a dental clinic, shoe
stores, and beauty salons. At the center
of it all are Daniel Kim and his mother
Shinocho shaking hands, cutting ribbons,
growing the empire. And for a long time,
no one knew what's really going on
behind the scenes at Grace Road.
We're trying to uncover what's really
happening here. During his long flight
to Fiji, Voli put his time to good use,
improving his problem solving and
logical thinking skills with the help of
our sponsor, Brilliant. Brilliant is a
hands-on learning platform that offers
thousands of visual interactive lessons
from math and AI to programming. Here,
for example, you have to make the green
duck disappear with a function. You
learn by doing, [music] which is up to
six times more effective than
traditional lectures. We also really
enjoy training our logical thinking this
way. Don't be fooled by the cute
animations. The puzzles get more and
more challenging over time. All courses
were crafted by teachers, researchers,
and experts from renowned institutions.
Brilliant is available as an app as well
as on your PC or laptop. Scan this QR
code or go to brilliant.org/fern [music]
and start learning new skills with
Brilliant. With our link, you'll get 20%
off their annual subscription, giving
you access to everything the platform
has to offer.
>> We are actually driving to NA right now,
which is the place where it all started.
The headquarters of Grace Roads, Grace
Farms. This is the road, the Grace Road.
During his travels, Voli is supported by
Lonnie, a filmmaker from Fiji. Behind
the scenes, Jim and Lada handle
logistics and access, and Mary does the
driving. Even before Voli arrived, they
tried to get us in touch with Grace
Road, sending emails and calling dozens
of numbers.
>> So, it was either not working, diverted,
or it had that fax line sound where this
high beeping sound when you call the
number. Two of them actually managed to
um get through. [music]
spoke to a lovely gentleman on one of
the numbers that I called and he said,
you know, email the admin. Email the
admin address. So, I did. I'm still
waiting for a response um from them.
I've tried that number again. Nobody's
answered
>> by now. It seems Lonnie's number got
blocked.
>> As we're approaching Grace Road
headquarters now, uh what's what's our
plan? Um, so I'm just going to go up to
the front door and speak to them and
explain to them what we're trying to do
in person and if we can really schedule
the time to sit down with them to have a
chat on camera.
>> Yeah.
>> Lonnie and Jim enter the building. After
a while, they return.
>> Come on. Why are you walking so slow? We
want to know. What did they tell you?
>> We've went up to the office.
>> They were nervous when we when we
mentioned the fact that we were part of
a documentary crew and we want to speak
to somebody. You could sort of feel the
shift in the vibe.
>> They didn't want to give some direct
contact or some address or
>> I asked for a number. They said no.
>> Police said no. Just let me in.
>> Voli can't film inside Grace Roads
headquarters or speak with officials,
but he can at least visit the Colts
restaurants.
>> I love I love the food that they have,
the menu that they prepare.
>> The pizzas are good.
>> I mean, they have good taste, especially
for the pizza. I love the pizza. It's a
It's a great place to eat.
>> I like their food and coffee.
>> Okay, we're at Olive Tree and uh I'm
having some carbonara rice cakes
and I have to say it's really really
good. We are at uh Pacifica and Fierce
Chicken having a coffee. So, the coffee
is good. I can tell you that. And the
rest I'll tell you a bit later.
>> So, let's take a look. Great food,
modern interior. No signs of an abusive
doomsday cult. But wait, these signs
read, "The brightest, cleanest, kindest,
and most honest eternal group that sees
and delivers the eternal love of God."
Interesting world map. Also, the center
of the world, Fiji, the only island with
yesterday and today. And look at these.
The booklet of truth by Reverend
Okoshin. Folly takes one justification
of threshing.
Reading about why Oxin has to be
released from prison,
it feels like everyone knows about Grace
Roads. Everyone has a reaction whenever
I mention the name. And I can't really
tell what the reaction is like about
their businesses, restaurants, shops.
But whenever I ask a little bit more
critical question, it feels people tense
up. People don't want to comment. people
don't know or they've heard some rumors,
but it really feels like they don't
speak openly or they can't speak openly
[music] or they just want to focus on
the positive aspects. And we have
speculated that this might also be
related to some kind of leftover fear of
the previous government which was
essentially a dictatorship under
Bimarama.
>> In the BI Marama era, things were quite
different. This is Fred Wesley,
editor-inchief of the newspaper Fiji
Times. He was already in office when
Grace RH set foot in Fiji. Back then,
what looked like paradise was in fact a
deeply oppressed country.
>> I say there's a lot of misunderstanding
by the international community of what
transpired here and Australia and New
Zealand [music] being big brothers uh
wanted to uh stamp their mark as big
brothers. But why do you think they're
doing it?
>> Because they don't like to see a
military dictatorship [music] in the
region. Frank Bay Imama came to power in
a military coup. He was a former
commodor of the Fijian Navy. He's a
strong man. He is reputed to have
inflicted great many acts of violence on
individuals who are critical of the
regime. A lot of people don't want to
understand the situation here. Is it
because I'm a military man?
>> Yes, of course. You've seized power.
Okay. you know, with a military man in a
nice shirt, but you're still a military
man and you still
>> I keep telling everyone a
[clears throat] radical change needs to
be brought in [music] and radical change
cannot be brought in by some weak
organization.
>> Under Bayam Marama, the opposition in
parliament was for all intents and
purposes muzzled. Freedoms of
expression, peaceful assembly and
association were restricted. Violence
was common place. The media was heavily
censored and tightly controlled by the
regime. I had a senior journalist who
was um uh based in the west uh who was
arrested five times uh thrown into a
cell three times. I've had uh people who
were journalists who were verbally
abused by ministers, you know, and uh an
editor would uh get a 20,00 $25,000 fine
and be sentenced to jail for 2 years.
>> It wasn't only journalists that were
suffering this kind of repression. The
laws were changed. The constitution was
changed. The arm of government was
strengthened in terms of repressing
negative or critical voices. It was a
very very strict regime for anybody who
wasn't completely aligned with the Bay
Marma agenda.
After seizing power in the 2006 coup,
Bayamaram held on thanks to a system
that mixed regular democratic elections
with periods of repression. He survived
two elections in 2014 and 2018. But in
2022, Fiji's economy is faltering. The
pandemic battered tourism and some sense
a wind of change. Benamar lost his
absolute majority and a coalition of
other parties took over parliament.
Voli still senses the echo of these dark
days of oppression, especially when he
talks to people off camera. Much of it
he puts down in his notes. Jim and Lani
often refer to the Banimarama regime, 16
years of oppression. They tell the story
of the relationship between Prime
Minister Bimarama and Grace Road. During
his tenure, the Fiji Development Bank
invested [music] a significant amount of
money in the group. On the other hand,
he used Grace Road for his own purposes.
From a Fijian perspective, the story of
Grace Road is bigger than the cult
itself. It's politically charged. The
OCCP investigated these troubling ties
between Bayamama and Grace [music] Road.
A former government spokesman told them
the cult was treated like a protected
species. Laws restricting free speech
also kept criticism of the cult largely
[music] muted. OCCRP revealed that
Fijian police had spoken with witnesses
who [music] described beatings and other
abuses by Grace Road members, but
without any serious consequences for
them. And so I think the the kind of
strongarmed administration that we see
in Grace Road would have resonated very
much with Frank Bay and Ayazed Caum, the
two main members of the Fijian
government at the time.
>> It's Voli's fifth day in Fiji and it
starts with a surprise. We've actually
received an answer from Grace Road, but
not the one we expected.
>> Okay. Here's a serious update.
Yesterday, Lani got a call from the film
commission in Fiji.
>> Wait, wait. Okay. Okay. Wait. Are you
Are you in the office?
>> Okay. I'll come across to you now.
>> Okay. Lonnie just got a phone call from
Film Fiji, who gave us the permit to
film that the lawyers of Grace Road
called Film Fiji to revoke our permit.
And right now, Lonnie is in the office.
So, the lawyers have contacted them
about the fact that we've been going to
different uh Grace Road restaurants and
shops and stuff. They're they're
emailing them now about cancelling
revoking the permit all together, the
filming permit altogether.
>> Losing the permit would mean that we'd
have to stop filming. Lonnie explained
to the commission that we didn't do
anything illegal at Grace Road, but now
she still has to deal with the lawyers.
>> So, I'm going to start
>> typing up emails now
>> again. Okay. Maybe maybe they can
actually get us in touch with Grace
themselves. Exactly. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Let's hope this all comes to a,
you know, fruitful outcome for
everybody.
>> Damn. Damn. Damn. Damn. This is getting
intense.
>> Everyone starts to um be aware of us.
Exciting.
>> The lawyers from Grace Road state that
>> our client is extremely concerned with
the basis on which a permit was given to
your production company. It is
imperative that the permits given to
your production company must be
cancelled for with. However, we will
leave that decision to film Fiji. They
also wrote that we need permission
[music]
from Grace Roads to film anything about
them and that they quote expressly
declines your request to film or shoot
any short film, documentary, or any
other form of any motion picture on or
about it. They're trying to shut us
down. If that's not a red flag, I don't
know what is.
Anyway, we get to keep our filming
permit, but from Grace Rose's
perspective, it probably made sense to
try to stop us from filming. After all,
it would be a shame if more people
learned about the horrendous crimes they
allegedly committed.
It's the summer of 2018, 4 years after
Grace Road's arrival in Fiji. Their many
businesses are thriving. Bayamaram's
regime is still in power. Shin is on a
15-our trip back to South Korea. When
she and other church leaders arrive at
Inshian International Airport in Seoul,
the group is suddenly surrounded by
police officers. Shinukjo and three of
her companions are arrested on the spot.
By that time, there were fairly
welldeveloped
allegations of uh significant physical
violence. The church goes through this
process they call the threshing floor.
And that means, you know, they say that
people's sins are expedated through
beatings effectively. It's really
upsetting violence.
>> We've seen the footage of the threshing
floor. We will not show it here, but it
is truly gruesome.
>> That kind of activity had been going on
for quite some time. Korean authorities
were aware of it. They had credible
allegations. They felt they had
sufficient evidence.
>> And these violent practices are said to
have made their way to Fiji. It appears
to be the method of maintaining
discipline within the church membership
itself. And that discipline is extremely
strict by every account that we've we've
come across. That's what Mara Ma told us
as well. She worked for Grace Roads
Farms and in their true mark
supermarkets.
>> They get in head but tell each other or
go to the hospital.
>> We were not able to independently verify
Marrama's statements. However, her
account aligns with numerous other
reports from former workers, including
those of this young woman whom Vali
happened to meet by chance on the
roadside.
>> If they did something wrong, they'll be
getting the I heard that they'll get
high level from the from the leaders and
the time they'll say that I fell. We
were not able to independently verify
her statements either. But she claims
that she worked at Grace Farms for 2
months as a holiday job. Despite the
harsh conditions for all employees, one
thing stands out. Grace Road seems to
operate like a two-tier society. On one
side are the local Fijians who have had
some bad experiences and on the other
the Koreans who have suffered far worse.
Fijian workers by all accounts were
treated well, but at the end of the day,
they went home. The mostly Korean uh
church members did not. They were kept
in barracks. There have been a number of
allegations. They extend to separation
of family members forcefully, the
unwilling detention of people taking
their passports effectively and refusing
them the ability to travel, that is to
leave the church. There have been
allegations of being fed improperly,
being housed improperly, being
overworked, uh, well beyond what normal
labor practices would allow, physical
punishments. To top everything off,
much of this was allegedly also
experienced in 2014 by then 21-year-old
Suan Lee. After undergoing cancer
surgery, her mother joined Grace Road
and wanted to travel to Fiji for
recovery. Suan interrupted her studies
and accompanied her for 2 weeks. Shin's
sermons were bizarre.
>> A lot of [music] wailing, a lot of
shouting. She would verbally abuse a lot
of people, call the names, awful names.
>> When she tried to leave, she realized
something was wrong.
>> Actually, I started packing the day
before. And when I went to, you know,
pack my computer, my laptop, um, it was
gone. I realized my passport was gone. I
was panicking a lot. Um, I was screaming
for help. Dressed only in pajamas and
flip-flops, she made [music] her escape.
Although others tried to block her path,
she managed to break free and ran
straight towards a police car. They
helped her obtain an emergency passport
at the South Korean embassy. All the
while, Grace Road members pursued her,
and even her own mother tried to
convince her to stay, but she left her
mother behind in Fiji and managed to
return to South Korea.
Grace Road seems to rule over its
members with an iron fist. The cult runs
an enormous business [music] empire and
has excellent ties to the country's
dictator. So, they may have wondered,
why not bring the promised land under
its control entirely? [music]
While Shin settles into a prison cell,
South Korean authorities are continuing
their crackdown on Grace Road. Shortly
after capturing Shin and Seoul, they
plan to strike again. 17 officers are
sent on a secret mission to Fiji. On the
ground, they meet with the local police.
And in the middle of the night, a joint
operation begins. They arrived at the
main multi-acre farm. That's the
headquarters of the church. Late at
night, did a sort of a sweep to gather
up people and evidence uh before anybody
had a chance to react.
>> In the following days, six South Korean
citizens get arrested, including Shin's
son, Daniel Kim. The secret mission is
looking like a huge success. But then,
>> well, nobody really knows exactly what
happened. What we do know is that uh the
courts intervened quite quickly. Shortly
after that intervention, the Fijian
police were saying, "Okay, look, we're
going to take over this investigation."
And so the the Korean police detachment
who thought that they were going to come
back with, you know, a number of people
in their custody ended up going back
empty-handed. An Interpol red notice was
issued uh at around that time for Daniel
Kim and presumably for others.
But in Fiji, it seems like no one cares.
Perhaps investigations continue behind
the scenes, but for years nothing comes
of them.
So Daniel Kim gets to carry on with
business as usual. Grace Road launches
new ventures and keeps on growing. They
expanded from 30 something businesses to
54 in the period following the raids.
Grace Road became one of the largest
private employers in Fiji at the time.
>> And they keep diversifying from dental
clinics to gas stations. The stations
are reportedly run in partnership with
Exxon Mobile. They are still operating
today. We asked Exxon Mobile whether
they were aware of the events
surrounding Grace Road and why instead
of ending the cooperation, they chose to
expand it. They did not respond.
In July 2019, Shinukjo was convicted in
South Korea. She was sentenced to 6
years in prison for fraud, holding her
followers captive in Fiji and subjecting
them to violence.
>> Daniel Kim became the effective leader
of the church. He's got, you know, the
money of his contributors, of his church
members. He's also got access to a great
deal of leverage uh in terms of
development loans and various other
things.
>> But not everyone in Fiji stays silent
about Grace Road. At the end of 2019,
opposition leader Sideni Rabuka demands
an immediate investigation. Now, the
Korean courts have convicted the founder
of Grace Road for offenses committed in
Fiji, our authorities cannot turn a
blind eye to the allegation of forced
labor, torture, assault, and illegal
detention. and they must act swiftly to
protect the human rights of the members
of Grace Road and prosecute those who
have broken our laws. Despite all the
allegations and calls for investigation,
Bayamaram reportedly continues to let
the cult operate undisturbed for years.
But by 2022, his grip on power is
slipping. After 16 years of oppressive
rule, Bayamaram is finally voted out.
Sideni Rabuka becomes prime minister.
All signs point to trouble for Grace
Road.
2023 September 7th. The newly elected
Fijian government is cracking down on
the cult. Six members of the cult are
declared prohibited immigrants after the
South Korean government nullified their
passports. Two members get deported. Two
more are released after a court
injunction. The last two, including
Daniel Kim, are said to be on the run.
But then this appears on Facebook.
We are not.
We everyone we know who knows about us.
Do we look like a per if the per why the
so many of the customers supportings? So
I want to deliver this message to the
people that this is not a legal thing.
This is this is unleally and we are not
happy about it. How they can do that?
>> But it's no use. Daniel Kim is put on
immigration custody. For years, Grace
Road stayed silent in the face of
criticism. But now they launch a massive
solidarity campaign. The cult is facing
existential risks. Its leader was
convicted in South Korea. Her son, the
new head, is detained and the new
government has launched extensive
investigations. For now, their business
keeps running. From agriculture and
construction to restaurants,
supermarkets, and gas stations, the
question is how long will it last? A
concern that it seems has begun to
trouble the Fijian government as well.
Grace Road claims in a statement that it
creates jobs for rural development and
employs over 800 local workers, making
it one of the country's biggest
employers. Well, look, you know, let's
be let's be realistic. Grace Road is a
significant economic driver. Tourism has
not rebounded to the levels that um
existed precoid. Grace Road is an
alternative employer to the tourism
industry. And so if you pull the plug,
you know, summarily on 54 companies
operating across swath of the country's
main island, that could have some pretty
serious repercussion.
Jump forward to December 2024, 400 days
after Kim's detention, half a year
before Vali will travel to Fiji.
Countless Grace Road members and
employees have gathered in front of the
appeals court in the capital, Suva. This
is the moment they have all been waiting
for. Daniel Kim and another Grace Road
official step out.
He is free.
>> This was a sort of a the normal
operation of the courts. They have
allowed him his liberty while uh [music]
this judicial review is in process. The
de facto leader of Grace Road is out on
bail. No one back in Fiji has been
prosecuted for their alleged [music]
practices behind closed doors. I know
there are great many people who feel
that there should be prosecutions. That
is not a view that's shared by the
public prosecutor in Fiji at this time.
Even the US government criticizes Fiji
in its newly released report on human
trafficking. The report notes that no
one from Grace Road has ever been
prosecuted or convicted.
A clear shift has taken place within the
Fijian government from the unmistakable
demands of the past to a far more
cautious approach. The government
publicly states that it's disappointed
that Grace Road is now reconsidering new
investments in Fiji. They stress that
they have always treated Grace Road with
friendliness and they say they respect
them for their new retail standards they
brought to Fiji. Currently there is a
great deal of concern about uh you know
what happens if you effectively kill
this golden goose you know if you remove
one of the substantial private sector
drivers in the Fijian economy at this
time.
Now on the ground, Voli wants to ask
government representatives about these
concerns, and we want to know why the
investigations into Grace Road keep
dragging on. According to the OCCP,
Fijian officers have spoken to key
witnesses of beatings and other abuses
more than 5 years ago. What's taking so
long? Interviews have been arranged, but
a series of unfortunate circumstances
got in the way. For example, key members
of the government were stuck on another
island 6 to 8 hours away. Now most of
the government officials actually like
this week they have a super intense week
right in the
>> luckily Lonnie has already received
commitments from individual ministers
and is now trying to arrange new
appointments but
>> now more than 2 weeks later this is her
message I spent Monday morning at
Kamikamita and Napoto's office trying to
lock interview times [music] both these
ministers have been advised not to make
any public comments regarding grace road
since both offices have active interests
and files before them any public
comments have a high chance of putting
both them and their ministry in a
precarious position.
>> We sent them written questions but never
received a reply. We also reached out to
the Grace Road group but unsurprisingly
got no response either.
Lani talked about the colonial history
of Fiji, how the UK thought they could
conquer [music] it but couldn't and
instead had to integrate. She has a
similar hope with Grace Road [music]
that outsiders coming to Fiji with bad
intentions might somehow be changed for
the better.
>> Right? You're saying, "Oh, well that's
okay. Over there, we still go and buy
their pizzas cuz their pizzas [music]
are good." You know, that kind of
thinking. Oh, well, no, that's the
chicken. That's not the church. That's
not No, it's all it's all connected.
[music] Our comfort and our convenience
is more important than our values and
our ethics. And I think that's where we
where [music] we start to fail as people
and as Christians. And you see, I came
here to understand what is grace road
really about. And to be honest, finding
answers to these questions has been
really, really tough. There's so much
secrecy. People seem to be afraid of
something [music] whenever talking about
grace roads.
>> I think one of the things that we need
to remember is that Fijians have been
living under a more or less oppressive
regime with significant curtailment of
their human rights since 2006. Dem
democratic government as we understand
it is a fairly novel concept.
Our latest investigation story [music]
or peace is with our lawyers. We've had
uh Grace Road Lawyers send us a notice
to holding back the story. But uh yes,
we do have uh an an investigation
[music] piece that we hope to run over a
couple of weeks uh an in-depth
investigation where we have spoken to
victims. We have spoken to people who
worked once for Grao and who have left.
>> As of the release of this video, the
Fiji Times have not published their
investigation.
>> So, while many of my questions are still
unanswered, there's at least one thing I
can say for sure, and that's the people.
I mean, the people of Fiji, they will
always stay my heart. They're the
nicest, most generous, humorous people.
Always up for a smile. Even though it's
not super easy to live here. I mean many
Fijians struggle to make a living to
make ends meet and it's also not a huge
country [music] and that's exactly why
outsiders coming in here as guests as
businesses as churches [music]
they must act with real care with
responsibility transparency and of
course I mean Grace Road [music] has
brought a lot of good things
>> without a doubt they have a business
model uh that's unique and without a
doubt they've actually stimulated
economic development, economic growth in
areas that didn't have this. They were
they've employed people. You know,
that's that's a reality. But there's
also a lot of negatives when so much
good is wrapped in so much secrecy, when
there is a taboo to speak about it at
all. That's that's really a red flag to
me and that tells me something has to be
changed.
What better place than this to read you
a little bit from uh Reverend Octusin's
brochure. This brochure is written by
Octusin from prison and uh given out
publicly in grace shops and I'll read
some more of this to you. Threshing an
assault moving to Fiji a confinement.
The threshing floor is the spiritual
warfare for the salvation of souls. The
spirit of truth, Reverend Octusin,
carried out the threshing floor to
protect the children of God from the
plagues. To us, this does not sound like
remorse. To us, this sounds like a
justification for brutal violence.
Meanwhile, Grace Road [music] seems to
be looking to expand their empire beyond
Fiji. the president of Nau, which is a
tiny island nation of about 20,000
people, um has extended an invitation to
Daniel Kim, asking him to come [music]
and work his economic magic on his tiny
island to see, you know, what what he
can do to help the economy of Naru.
>> Naru's climate is warm with no winter.
Fertile soil [music] is limited, though.
But who's to say if any of this is
really in preparation for some imaginary
apocalypse or just about money and
power?